<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>C# on Learnings in IT</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/c%23/</link>
    <description>Recent content in C# on Learnings in IT</description>
    <image>
      <title>Learnings in IT</title>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/images/papermod-cover.png</url>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/images/papermod-cover.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.149.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>©</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 01:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/c%23/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>URL Shortener in High Throughput Service</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/shortidgeneration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 01:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/shortidgeneration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Client has E-commerce Application consisting of services aimed at specific domains of business functionality it serves. One of these services is responsible for accepting the order, authenticating it and forwarding it for further processing in terms of inventory checks, payment and so on. For  Authentication, this service sends &lt;a href=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SMS
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;SMS&lt;/a&gt; to Customer&amp;rsquo;s  Mobile number (and e-mail id) and customer is supposed to confirm this order placement by means of entering Code received in it. This code is valid for a short duration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading API: Learnings</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/apiupgrade/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 01:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/apiupgrade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the design considerations stressed upon by Jeffrey richter about APIs (Read more &lt;a href=http://localhost:1313/posts/restapiversioning/
    
    
&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) is that &amp;ldquo;API is expected to be stable over long period of time&amp;rdquo;. Recently,for a .NET based project, we decided to upgrade some of the ASMX (legacy SOAP based approach) based APIs and were immediately reminded by Customer(s) to avoid any kind of impact on existing users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that upgrade must be done keeping in mind,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is WebAssembly future of Web Development</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/webassembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 10:25:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/webassembly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last many years, de-facto language of the Web (specifically front-end) has been Javascript (and variants like Typescript, ECMAScript versions and so on). The Web development has been revolving around HTML+CSS+Javascript trio. It all started with support for Javascript in browsers, followed by addition of XMLHTTP API, Rich DOM Manipulation Support in Javascript. To induce order and apply patterns to Javascript&amp;rsquo;s usage in browsers, numerous frameworks and libraries were introduced like &lt;a href=https://reactjs.org
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=https://vuejs.org
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Vue&lt;/a&gt; among others. To begin with, The target used to be browsers on Large Devices like Desktop &amp;amp; Laptops. However, soon all sorts of devices were targetted with advent of Responsive and Progressive CSS+Javascript libraries eg. &lt;a href=https://getbootstrap.com
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;. Offline Support soon came in ref: &lt;a href=https://electronjs.org
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Electron&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=https://web.dev/progressive-web-apps/
    
    target=_blank rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;
&gt;Progressive Web Applications&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
