<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Database on Learnings in IT</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/tags/database/</link><description>Recent content in Database on Learnings in IT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 01:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sachinsu.github.io/tags/database/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Database Reliability Engineering - My Notes</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/dbre/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 01:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/dbre/</guid><description>Introduction I have been reading excellent Database Reliability Engineering book and below are my notes from it.
Key Incentive(s) for Automation
Elimination of Toil - Toil is the kind of work tied to running a production service that tends to be manual, repetitive, automatable, tactical, devoid of enduring value, and that scales linearly as a service grows. Important System Characteristics
Latency, also known as response time, is a time-based measurement indicating how long it takes to receive a response from a request.</description></item><item><title>Presto - A distributed SQL Engine for variety of data stores</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/presto/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 10:25:04 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/presto/</guid><description>Introduction In a company/enterprise, typically there are multiple sources of data. This could be result of M&amp;amp;A (where each of those add in a new data store) or result of multi year process of using data stores that are in vogue at that time. Result is combination of various types of relational databases, flat file systems, queues and so on. This results in Data Silos. This scenario is typically observed in companies who are running workloads On-prem (i.</description></item></channel></rss>