<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Links on Learnings in IT</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/</link><description>Recent content in Links on Learnings in IT</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 12:33:07 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sachinsu.github.io/links/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Resources for Online Learning</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/onlearn/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 12:33:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/onlearn/</guid><description>Section covering resources for Online learning etc.
Exploring basics of Computer Science, bit by bit Exploring basics of Distributed Systems Awesome List of Free Learning Resources Collection of online learning resources Complete intro to Linux and CLI Linux System Administration - Skill challenge</description></item><item><title>Programming Languages - Python</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/python/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 14:13:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/python/</guid><description>Python has become pervasive all throught Data Science be it Machine learning, Deep learning, Data Processing and general purpose tasks like Web Development.
Courses, Trainings Python for Beginners from MSDN Nice Collection of trainings per level of complexity Python Programming And Numerical Methods: A Guide For Engineers And Scientists Articles Getting machine learning to production A quick-and-dirty guide on how to install packages for Python What to do when data doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit in memory Packages EasyOCR - supports 40+ languages Simplified Static file serving for Python Podcasts Talkpython</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intellgence, Machine Learning</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/aiml/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 14:13:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/aiml/</guid><description>Useful links related from AI, ML space
Collections Collection of resources related to Applied ML List of tools for MLOps Free courses Fast AI by Jeremy Howard Articles Machine Learning Algorithms: What is a Neural Network? What is Benford’s Law and why is it important for data science? Benford’s Law and Financial Statements Data Scientists Should Be More End-to-End Team Data science process (Microsoft) Traits of Good Data Scientist Videos Neural Networks Demystified Deep Learning: A Crash course</description></item><item><title>Cloud Tech</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/cloud/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 14:13:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/cloud/</guid><description>Useful links for deep diving in various Cloud Ecosystems
Articles Zero dollar Infrastructure stack Cloud Server Performance, Prices, Specs and Features Articles (GCP) 13 sample architectures to kickstart your Google Cloud journey Using Google Cloud Spanner locally &amp;hellip;using Emulator Articles (AWS) What a typical 100% Serverless Architecture looks like in AWS! Automating safe, hands-off deployments Containerizing legacy ASP.NET applications using AWS App2Container (A2C) Replacing web server functionality with serverless services AWS Lambda vs Cloudflare Workers Unbound One line Explaination for each of AWS Services Building a Multiplayer Game with API Gateway+Websockets, Go and DynamoDB Best Practices To Handle Lambda Timeout Errors Save 99.</description></item><item><title>UI/UX</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/uiux/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 15:07:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/uiux/</guid><description>User Interface / User Experience Design Approach How Stripe Designs Beautiful Websites Tools for non artistic developers Articles Comparing Polling vs WebSockets vs SSE A simple, choice-driven chatbot framework with Vanilla Javascript Centering in CSS: A Complete Guide Centering in CSS Full-bleed layout using CSS Grid Blog on HTML,fonts, Asynchronous JavaScript How to pick beautiful colors You dont need Javascript Sign in form Best practices How HTTP Range Requests work (for large file downloads etc.</description></item><item><title>Perspectives</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/perspectives/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2020 12:33:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/perspectives/</guid><description>Perspectives Section covering Business, project/programming perspectives
The New Business of AI (and How It’s Different From Traditional Software) Momentum vs Urgency in Software Project Management Data Science: Reality Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Meet Expectations Quantum computing for the very curious How to Speak (MIT) How Software Groups Rot: Legacy of the Expert Beginner What questions should systems architects ask before creating anything Basecamp for Personal Project Management Marketing for Engineers - Resources Approach to Exception Handling PRESALES (SE) LEADER?</description></item><item><title>Tools</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/tools/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2020 12:33:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/tools/</guid><description>General Purpose tools Section covering useful tools for every day activities, Online learning etc.
OBS Studio - Free and open source software for video recording and live streaming. Open source 3D parametric modeler Backstage - an open platform for building developer portals Zoomit - screen zoom and annotation tool for technical presentations that include application demonstrations revealjs - HTML Presentation framework Useful Command line tools Zmap - collection of open source tools for performing large-scale studies of the hosts and services that compose the public Internet.</description></item><item><title>Oracle</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/oracle/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 15:09:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/oracle/</guid><description>Oracle Database Performance, Best Practices Connection Strategies for Database Applications Using High-Speed Data Loading and Rolling Window Operations with Partitioning Designing Applications for Oracle Real-World Performance Best Practices for Extreme Performance with Oracle Data Warehousing Blog on Oracle Performance troubleshooting Using PL/SQL Bulk processing features Auditing tables using Oracle Flashback data archive instead of triggers Bulk processing with PL/SQL Bulk Processing with BULK COLLECT and FORALL Primer on Oracle Partitioning Database Core performance principles - Deck Database insert &amp;amp; referential integrity - Performance On Connection Pools, Cursor Differentiation, and Optimal Ordering Analytical Functions Overview About Materialized Views How to find Slow SQL Using External Tables and Table Clusters in Oracle Oracle DBA - Application Tuning Replacing Kafka use cases with Oracle Advanced queues in modern applications SQL Tips you can&amp;rsquo;t do without Change Data Capture Nice writeup on options to do CDC in Oracle Database Integrating Oracle and Kafka Videos Real world performance video series How to:Analyze AWR Report 5 Minutes Demo: Using Liquibase in SQLcl to version Oracle Database Analytic SQL for Developers - Free course Connection Pooling and SmartDB Oracle Database for Developers - Training How to Create an Execution plan?</description></item><item><title>PostgreSQL</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/postgresql/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 15:08:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/postgresql/</guid><description>PostgreSQL Links Using generate_series feature for reporting When Postgres blocks: 7 tips for dealing with locks PostgreSQL - Don&amp;rsquo;t do this Is PostgreSQL good enough? Online event processing by Martin Klepmann PostgreSQL rocks, except when it blocks: Understanding locks Connection handling best practice with PostgreSQL 10 Things I Hate About PostgreSQL PostgreSQL - Advanced Administration by Bruce Momjian Top Tools and Recommendations to Manage Postgres in an Enterprise: Administration, Performance, High Availability, and Migration Using PostgreSQL as Cache and Read Optimization tips Adyen&amp;rsquo;s Use of PostgreSQL PostgreSQL version Upgrade @ Gitlab Zombodb - PostgreSQL and ElasticSearch work together Using pg_cron to schedule background tasks PG Database Configuration Helper Full text search in PostgreSQL PostgreSQL - Best practices(Azure) Designing high performance time series data table in (RDS) postgresql Informative blog on PostgreSQL PostgreSQL - Using SQL for Data Analysis Approach to Bulk Import in PostGreSQL Performance tuning, configuration etc.</description></item><item><title>NOSQL</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/nosql/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 15:08:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/nosql/</guid><description>NOSQL Databases Amazon DynamoDB Data Modelling in DynamoDB Must follow Twitter handle of Rick Houlihan Best Practices for Secondary Indexes with DynamoDB Apache Cassandra 7 mistakes when using Apache Cassandra Apache Geode How Mastercard fights fraud with Apache Geode Apache Pinot Pinot- Enabling Real-time Analytics @ linkedin Redis Redis High Availability Redis Cluster KeyDB is a high performance fork of Redis with a focus on multithreading, memory efficiency, and high throughput.</description></item><item><title>MySQL</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/mysql/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 15:07:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/mysql/</guid><description>MySQL Links Query analytics for the day-to-day developer with MySQL 8.0 Schema Change Management for MySQL Temporal Data tables in MariaDB MySQL 8.0 Indexes, Histograms, and Other Ways to Speed Up Your Queries Maxwell - MySQL to Kafka change data capture LetsEncrypt setup for MariaDB How LetsEncrypt has built Next Gen Database Servers 18 things you can do to remove mysql Bottlenecks due to High traffic MySQL from Developer&amp;rsquo;s perspective Interesting libraries, extensions Distributed job-queue built specifically for queuing and executing heavy SQL read jobs asynchronously.</description></item><item><title>Databases</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/databases/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 15:02:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/databases/</guid><description>Database Knowledge base around general database related topics.
General Links Heimdall data -Database scale-out without Application changes Database of databases Modern SQL in databases Eventual consistency by Werner Vogels Amazon Aurora ascendant: How we designed a cloud-native relational database - All Things Distributed Options for scaling from 1 to 100,000 tenants Amazon Aurora: design considerations for high throughput cloud-native relational databases | the morning paper NOSQL - Key Points Criteria for Choosing Data store Building Real Time Analytics APIs at Scale Streaming Database Changes with Debezium Why you should pick strong consistency, whenever possible Change Data Capture, Outbox and Event Sourcing Using Streamsets for CDC From Oracle to Other destinations Transactions in Google Spanner Things I Wished More Developers Knew About Databases MySQL Sharding at Quora Interactive Book about SQL SQL Interview Questions Hadoop or Laptop The lightweight, distributed relational database built on SQLite Optimizing SQL Queries, Regardless of Platform How to do Data Modelling the right way Primer on Database Replication Connection pool sizing for databases Some SQL tricks from Application DBA Best Practices while writing SQL Using checksums to verify syncing 100M database records Data Engineering How tos- List of Curated Articles/Videos How to populate a table with 1 million records using single query How databases optimize Subqueries Tools Collection DBMS Tools Data Analytics Emerging Architectures for Modern Data Infrastructure Data Visualization/Exploration platforms Comparion Matrix Supercharging Apache Superset Redash - Collaboration, dashboards Why data culture matters Designing a data transformation that delivers value right from the beginning List of Computational Data Analysis Workflow Systems Data Visualization framework for Python Create a Serverless Data Lake on AWS and Migrate your On-Prem Data to it Analytics Academy by Segment Analytics Whitepapers by Sisense SQL Analytics Training A Beginner&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Data Engineering - 3-part series Chart types and its usage Rudder - Open source Customer Data Infrastructure DuckDB - Embeddable OLAP DBMS Data Lake - Solution Patterns Catalog of Widgets for Data Visualization Open source OLAP Database 1mg&amp;rsquo;s Data Stack A Unified Data Infrastructure Architecture Data and AI Product Landscape Transformations for DWH using DBT Awesome list of Business Intelligence Tools Article Series on Open source Data Analytics Stack (Postgres,Meltano, Airflow, dbt and Superset) Posthog - open source product analytics platform What is delta lakehouse?</description></item><item><title>Programming Languages - .NET</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/dotnet/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 14:14:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/dotnet/</guid><description>Microsoft .NET Platform where i have spent most time till now.
General Links What is .NET? by Scott Hanselman Async in Depth Using Async/Await in WCF or ASMX with AsyncEx .NET Presentations - Events in a Box Building Microservices in .NET Materialized View Pattern for Cross Service Queries Oracle DB &amp;amp; .NET - Optimizing Real-World Performance with Static Connection Pools Clean Code concepts and tools adapted for .NET Multiple ways how to limit parallel tasks processing Parallel programming in .</description></item><item><title>Programming Languages - Go</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/go/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 14:13:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/go/</guid><description>Go Language My current Favourite Language
Articles, E-books High performance GO Workshop Learnings from Production usage of Go Thoughts on Go performance optimization Effective Go Handling 1M websockets connections in Go Notes on Go language Standard Go Project Layout 10 things you (probably) don&amp;rsquo;t know about Go Useful patterns in Go Interesting ways of using Go channels How i writer web services in Go Embed static file(s) in Go Executable and expose over HTTP Using go:embed in Go 1.</description></item><item><title>Programming - Testing</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/testing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 14:05:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/testing/</guid><description>Testing Links How different software companies do testing HTTP(S) benchmark tools, testing/debugging, &amp;amp; restAPI (RESTful) Toxiproxy - A TCP proxy to simulate network and system conditions for chaos and resiliency testing</description></item><item><title>Programming Languages</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/planguages/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 13:38:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/planguages/</guid><description>Programming Languages Links Hello world in every Programming Language General You are not Google Production Launch Checklist Things I Learnt The Hard Way in 30 Years of Software Development A collection of (mostly) technical things every software developer should know Startup idea Checklist System Design Primer Developer Roadmaps Why our team cancelled our move to microservices How Does HTTPS Work? RSA Encryption Explained How do you cut a monolith in half?</description></item><item><title>Programming</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/programming/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 12:33:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/programming/</guid><description>System Design, Architecture Links covering concepts and approaches around Distributed Systems, DevOps, Observability etc.
Architectural Case studies Temenos Serverless banking at Scale @ AWS using CQRS leveraging RDS and DynamoDB Temenos @ AWS Architecture Diagrams Architecture for Generations Uber&amp;rsquo;s Domain-Oriented Microservice Architecture Strategies/Approaches Rob Pike&amp;rsquo;s 5 Rules of Programming Modules, monoliths, and microservices The macro problem with Microservices Break Monolith into Microservices Distributed architecture concepts I learned while building a large payments system Video: Developing Asynchronous Microservices • Chris Richardson Collection of Software development Videos Slides Managing Data Consistency in Microservices Architecture Reliable Microservices Data Exchange With the Outbox Pattern Scaling to 100k Users Monolith - Modular Approach You don&amp;rsquo;t need Microservices Event Modelling - Approach Ready for changes with Hexagonal Architecture How to fix Overloaded Web server How gov.</description></item><item><title>Useful Links</title><link>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/home/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 11:38:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/links/home/</guid><description>Below is list of curated links for various technical topics, Awesome - de-facto repository covering wide range of technical topics. Awesome list of self hosted software Online Learning Perspectives Distributed Systems Design, Architecture &amp;hellip; Testing UI/UX Languages Go .NET/C# Python Databases MySQL Oracle PostgreSQL NoSQL Cloud Tech AI, Machine Learning Machine Learning General Purpose tools Must follow Community Sites Hacker news Lobsters A list of SaaS, PaaS and IaaS offerings that have free tiers of interest to devops and infradev Miscellaneous Open Source alternative tools Useful tools for Windows by Scott Hanselman Library of Free music Ergonomic Home office setup Consider upgrading a few PC/laptop Components like SSD How to use Google like a pro</description></item></channel></rss>