<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on SachinSunkle</title>
    <link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on SachinSunkle</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 10:25:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ASP.NET Core - Mind the SameSite HTTP Cookie settings</title>
      <link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/samesitecookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 10:25:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/samesitecookies/</guid>
      <description>Background A Web Application, developed in ASP.NET Core (Runtime Version 3.1.100) using Razor Pages and Web API, is expected to be launched from within third-party Web Application in iframe, with complete HTML being rendered.
During the Development, a mock HTML Page was developed to simulate launching of ASP.NET core based Web Application in iframe. Note that this page as well as Application was hosted on same IIS Server and it worked fine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Channels for High performance Producer consumer implementation</title>
      <link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/channelsforproducerconsumer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 10:25:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/channelsforproducerconsumer/</guid>
      <description>Using Channels to implement Producer Consumer pattern Background Recently, i got involved in assignment where in an application was facing issues with throughput. Expectation is to support more than 500 transactions per second while load testing results were indicating system was experiencing high latency beyond 100+ transactions per second.
This application is developed in .NET Framework + .NET Core and primarily uses Relational Database for persistence and has point to point integration (mainly over HTTP) with internal &amp;amp; external application(s).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using .NET standard Assembly in .NET core and .NET Framework</title>
      <link>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/dotnetstandard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 10:25:04 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sachinsu.github.io/posts/dotnetstandard/</guid>
      <description>Using .NET standard Assembly in both .NET core and .NET Framework Background One of the key project(s) at my current organization is developed on .NET 4.6.1. It is developed as Modular Monolith. As part of it&amp;rsquo;s functionality, it supports different channels like Mobiles, Terminals and Web. For the Web channel, there was need to develop a Web application with,
 High availability Lightweight, High throughput (Need to support few thousand(s) active users)  Accordingly, we have been exploring developing this Web Application in .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>